Subindex build by Linnet
http://linnet.126.com  http://blog.csdn.net/redbirdli
火鸟字幕合并器SubindexV0.4 绿色软件联盟www.xdowns.com
Build time 12.04.12 09:08:20
字幕： Circle did it for Joan
校对： 小霸王比比?  ＆娃娃
规则第1条：一定要了解目标的居住环境
Rule No. 1: Be sure to know everything about those you visit.
第2：不要耽搁超过 10分钟
2: Never use more than ten minutes.
每多花一分钟 就增加了被人发现的风险
Because each minute increases the chance of someone coming home unexpectedly.
第3：不要留下任何DNA证据
3: Do not leave any DNA.
第4 不要浪费时间，在值不了多少的赝品上
4. Do not waste your time obtaining an expensive copy.
仿冒的再逼真 迟早会被发现
Even with trivial simple forgeries it takes weeks before being detected.
第5：该来的总会来的
5: Sooner or later one of two things has to happen.
只要得到一件稀世珍宝，那下半辈子都不用愁了
You will find a work of art so valuable you don't have to worry about anything.
不然就是去吃牢饭
Or you will get caught.
片名： 猎头游戏
我叫做罗杰布朗 我只有168公分高
My name is Roger Brown. I am 1.68 m.
说我心里不平衡吧，要做些补偿
You do not need a psychologist to understand that it must be compensated.
例如，我挑高天花板的房子：三千万 （1.5亿台币）
My house, for example. Ceiling: 30 million.
我不喜欢，也买不起 但是她... 她喜欢
I do not like it, and can't afford it. But she loves it.
你有很多像我一样要开画廊的朋友？
How often do you have a girlfriend who opens a gallery?
我都跟别人说这是遗产 其实我继承的东西是别的
I said it was an inheritance. Something I had to say. But I have just inherited bad genes.
‘神探专访’ 要发觉真相，是一个繁琐的过程
It has been a tedious process to find out the truth.
像我这样的人如果说还缺什么，也只有一样：
If like me someone wants to get what he wants, there is only one thing:
钱 很多很多的钱
Money. A lot of money.
可是戴安娜认为 还有一样比什么都重要
But there is one thing Diana wants more than anything else.
而那却是我唯一不想给她的东西
And that's just the thing I do not want to give her.
- 她是不是很可爱？ - 非常可爱
- Isn't she cute? - Very cute.
我的妻子戴安娜是最美丽的人，高挑又聪明
Diana Strm-Eliassen is on of the most beautiful, tall, smart.
她在这个世界上 想要什么都能得到
On of those accustomed to love. Those who take it for granted.
很多男人都会愿意为她付出 尤其那些身高超过 168的人
And lots of men want to give her that. Men who are taller than 1.68.
然而是我追求到她 因为我会把握机会
But soon it's my turn. My opportunity. I can feel it.
于此同时，我也去玩 因为不能放松玩乐的人，不会成功
In the meantime, I play loud. For he who does not play, will not win.
- 你明天要做什么？ - 问这要干嘛？
- What are you doing tomorrow? - Why do you ask?
有人请我们去吃饭
We are invited to dinner.
- 有人请我们去吃饭？ - 是啊
- We are invited to dinner? - Yes.
- 你跟别人说我们的事？ - 只有一个，我想介绍你们认识
- Are you talking about us with others? - There is one I want you to meet.
我们玩完了 我很抱歉
This ends now. I really am sorry.
- 我只是想... - 不行 罗悌 ...
- Let me be ... - No. Lotte ...
- 我们之间没什么 - 我们之间没什么？
- There is no us. - Isn't there?
- 一个令人印象深刻的履历，兰德 - 谢谢您！
- An impressive resume, Lander. - Thank you.
事实上，我觉得我就是‘探路者’要找的人
Yes, I think I am the right man for Pathfinder.
- 你的休闲时间都做些什么？ - 我哪来的时间休息啊
- What do you do in your spare time? - Is there such a thing?
你住在奥斯陆 妻子叫做...？
You live in Oslo. In Skyen. And you're married to ...?
卡蜜拉  结婚9年了 有两个孩子 都还在上学
Camilla. Been married for nine years. Two children. They go to school.
- 她也上班？ - 是的 在市中心的律师事务所
- She working? - Yes. In a law office in the center.
- 如果孩子生病在家谁顾？ - 她会顾
- Who is at home if a child is sick? - She is.
- 没请佣人？ - 没有
- No domestic help? - No.
- 有养狗？ - 没有
- Dog? - No.
- 会过敏？ - 不会
- Allergies? - No.
作为一个领导者 您的声誉如何？
What is your reputation as a leader worth?
我的声誉？是什??么意思？
My reputation? What do you mean?
那些画是朱利安?奥贝的作品 市值25万 （125万台币）
The plant was founded by Julian Opie. Worth a quarter of a million.
- 你有收藏这种价位的艺术品吗？ - 事实上，我有
- Do you own art in the price range? - Yes, actually.
一幅蒙克的版画 ‘胸针’
A lithograph by Munch. A brooch.
你知道如何监赏艺品的价值吗？
Can you see what it's worth just by looking at it?
那只是一些简单着色，单调的圆形和线条
This consists of circles and lines. Monotone coloring, without texture.
之所以价值 25万，是艺术家的名字
The thing that makes it worth a quarter of a million, is the artist's name.
- 这道理同样适用于领导者？ - 正是如此
- And the same goes for leaders? - Exactly.
这就是你无法得到这份工作的原因
And that is why you will not get this job.
- 什么？ - 天哪，你不该只身前来
- What? - Oh my God, you arranged it yourself.
- 我该怎么做呢？ - 必须由别人来介绍你这个人
- What else could I do? - Made someone to tell us about you.
听起来你没有体会我的意思，也许是联系得不够
Sounded like you were not aware of it when we contacted you.
要把它弄成一场秀，兰德 听着 ...
Everything is a game, Lander. Listen now ...
探路者的董事长和财务经理，明天都会来
Pathfinders Chairman and financial manager will come tomorrow.
我希望你们碰个面 礼貌上的
I want you to meet them. Listen politely.
你要表现得其实你不在意这个职位
How do you explain why you are no longer interested.
- 他们会觉得我很虚假 - 不. 你要野心勃勃
- They will perceive me as unserious. - No. As ambitious.
要表现的你清楚自己的价值
As someone who knows his own value.
- 兰德，这是你的机会 - 机会？
- Lander, this is your opportunity. - Possibility?
让我来帮你建立声誉
Let me build your reputation.
我保证你在两年内 就会找到五倍于现有收入的工作
I will promise you a job with five times your salary in two years.
你要怎么保证？
How can you promise that?
因为我从来没有给过客户，任何没有价值的意见
Because I have never given a customer a recommendation that he has not followed.
- 要怎么做呢？ - ‘作者的名字’
- But how? - The answer begins with "R".
- 声誉... - 会帮助你推展整个事业
- Reputation ... - The whole career is based on it.
你好
Hello.
您跟那位耶利米兰德以及‘探路者’ 明天12点开会
You have an interview with Jeremiah Lander and Pathfinder tomorrow at 12.
- 文件里有细节 - 是的 好
- The information is in the file. - Yes. Good.
你妻子的画廊这个周末开幕，我在想...
Your wife's supposed to open a gallery this weekend, and I was wondering ...
- 我是否能去呢？ - 你有被邀请吗？
- Is it possible to go there? - Are you invited?
- 我有，我能去吗？ - 你说呢？
- Yes, do I do it? - Will you?
我收到了卡斯帕汉森街 整修费 35万7千元的发票 （台币180万）
I have received an invoice for 357 000 for renovations in Kasper Hansen Street.
对 我帮戴安娜出的钱 她周五画廊要开幕
Right. I have helped Diana with expenses. She opens the gallery on Friday.
你该削减开支了，你现在随时会破产
You need to cut down on spending. You can go bankrupt at any time.
我会搞定的
I'm working on it.
我必须告诉你的情况是多么严重
I must tell you how serious the situation is.
你已经透支了几十万的卡...
You have overdrawn the card with several hundred thousand ...
我要接另一通电话 晚点打给你
I have another phone call here. I'll call you later.
有一个新目标 叫耶利米兰德，住在奥斯陆
You have a candidate. Jeremiah Lander, lives in Skyen.
- 没错 是我们公司的 什么时候？ - 明天12点在阿尔法开会
- Yes. We have him. When? - A meeting at the Alfa tomorrow at 12.
- 家中无人？ - 没有 他的妻子在市区工作
- No one home? - No. His wife works in the city.
我们二十分后见
We meet about twenty.
‘的黎波里’保全公司
哥德堡收赃物的人，要抽百分之五十
The fence in Gothenburg would get fifty percent.
他 奥雅纳 将获得 20％，负责关闭保全警铃
Ove Kjikerud would get 20% for disabling the alarm, get the art -
还有将艺品带到瑞典
- and run to Sweden with it.
请到在‘的黎波里’保全上班的他 可能是我做过的最明智的事情之一
To hire him in Tripoli was probably one of the smartest things I had done.
虽然这样我只能分到八万  八万！ （40万台币）
Although I was left with 80 000. 80 000!
它甚至还不够付下一季的房贷
It was not even for the next quarterly installment of the house.
必须另外再想办法
Something must be done.
您好！感谢你们的到来
Hello. Thank you for coming.
- 好盛大的场合 - 还有一半的客人还没来勒
- It does look very good. - Half of them have not arrived yet.
- 我有好多人要招呼 ... - 嘿，一切都会顺利的
- But I do not have to meet ... - Hey, it will go very well.
- 恭喜 刚的表演太棒了 - 谢谢您！
- Congratulations. Fantastic show. - Thank you.
真是疯狂的一天 我现在还不能放松
This has been a wild day. I can not tell it now.
- 有个人介绍给你认识 - 是谁？
- But I want you to meet him. - Meet with whom?
- 这是我的丈夫 罗杰布朗 - 我叫柯乐斯 格雷夫
- This is my husband. Roger Brown. - Clas Greve.
柯乐斯刚从荷兰 搬来挪威
Clas has just moved here. From the Netherlands.
你好，你要去吗？不，孩子们会很高兴的
Hello, are you going? No, the kids just cheer up.
- 来挪威是为了什么？工作？ - 我来继承我祖母的公寓
- What brings you to Norway? Work? - I inherited my grandmother's apartment.
- 她是挪威人？ - 没错
- She was Norwegian? - Yes.
我提前退休 所以要装修公寓
I retired early. I'm going to renovate the apartment.
退休？哪一行？
Retired? From what?
我是一家荷兰科技企业的董事
I was a director of a Dutch technology enterprise.
主要从事 GPS 全球定位系统...我们...
We worked mainly with GPS. Shall we ...?
- 荷兰的？该不会是‘贺得’吧？ - 是的，没错
- Dutch? Not Hote, right? - Yes, exactly.
他不是才刚要被一家美国大公司收购了？ 谷津科技 ？
Were not they just bought up by a large American company? Amtech?
- 您也是同行吗？ - 不是
- You work yourself in the industry? - No.
- 你为什么离开？ - 我谈公事烦你不好吧
- Why did you leave? - Let me not bore you with work talk.
我在招聘领域工作 已经习惯了这类谈话
I work in the recruitment industry. You do not bore me out with work talk.
- 你知道‘探路者’吗？ - 当然 是我们的竞争对手
- Do you know Pathfinder? - Of course. Our competitors.
小而美的公司
Small. Skilled.
我该走了... 祝您晚安
I must go. Have a good evening.
柯乐斯 ...探路者在找一个新的经理人
Clas ... Pathfinder seeks a new boss.
一个能抵御国外收购企图的人
One that can withstand takeover attempts from abroad.
- 要不要来一起开个会？ - 抱歉 我...
- Shall we have a meeting? - Sorry.
周一12点一起午餐 我们也可以谈谈别的事
A lunch. Monday at 12. We can talk about something else.
艺术，装修，请外籍工人...
Arts, renovation, Polish workers ...
我写餐厅的名字给你 好地方
I will write down the name of a good restaurant.
我好像恭敬不如从命
You do not take no for an answer?
公司给你的退休临别礼物？
A parting gift for a long and faithful service?
不，是我偷拿的
No, I stole it.
到时后见 向你迷人的妻子问候
When we meet. Say hello to your charming wife.
- 这是我的丈夫 - 罗杰布朗
- This is my husband. - Roger Brown.
- 我是布雷德，刑事调查局 - 电视上的神探本人
- Brede Sperre, Criminal Investigation Department - You have been on TV.
- 他在调查艺术品盗窃案 - 不是凶杀案？
- He investigates art thefts. - Not murder?
我们正全力调查本案 我一定要抓到他
We employ all resources on this. We must stop it.
- 你也在艺术产业？ - 不，我在一家猎头公司工作
- Are you in the art industry? - No. I work as a headhunter.
- 是人力仲介业 ‘阿尔法’ - 你是那家公司的股东之一
- In the recruitment industry. Alfa. - One of the partners, that is.
我刚刚正在称赞你妻子的美丽耳环
I gave your wife a compliment for those exclusive earrings.
- 她说，是你送的礼物 - 没错
- She said they were a gift from you. - Yes.
是的，我们公司的分红机制不错
Yes, the best of us good bonus schemes.
真好，我们警察的福利也这样就好了
I wish that we had it in my industry as well.
警探？我们是《VG》报  能拍张照吗？
Sperre? From VG. Could we have a picture?
好的
Sure.
罗杰？来一下
Roger? Will you?
看看这个  ‘卡吕冬野猪的狩猎’，鲁本斯的名画
See this. The search for The Calydonian Boar Hunt, by Rubens.
1941年在安特卫普被德国人偷了
Stolen by Germans in Antwerp in 1941.
从那时起就没人见过，你知道它现在挂在哪吗？
Since then it has been missing. Do you know where it hangs now?
- 不知 - 在柯乐斯格雷夫 奥斯卡街的公寓里
- No. - Clas Greve apartment in Oscars Street.
他的祖母在战争期间与位德国军官有秘密往来
His grandmother had a secret relationship with a German officer during the war.
战后，他被逮捕，几天被处死
Then he was arrested, and shot a few days later.
- 她怕被发现 到处躲藏 - 而且她把画藏起来？
- She was afraid she would be discovered. - And so she hid the painting?
- 但事实并非如此 - 德国人交出来的是复制品？
- But that's not true. - Collected Germans reproductions?
- 他为什么要告诉你？ - 他想找人做秘密的估价
- Why did he tell you? - He would have an independent evaluation.
问我是否有熟识的行家
Asked if I knew someone who could do it.
柯乐斯有一幅真正的鲁本斯名画，就在他的公寓里？
Clas Greve has a genuine Rubens painting in his apartment?
- 就在奥斯陆这里？ - 没错！
- Here in Oslo? - Yes.
我提议还是接洽美术馆，先把它移到那里
I offered to contact an art museum, to get it moved there.
下个礼拜...这样一幅名画 不应该深锁在保险箱里
Next week. Such a picture should not be only put in a safety deposit box.
- 你觉得它值多少钱？ - 好几千万 也许上亿 （Circle:五亿台币！）
- How much do you think it is worth? - Tens of millions. Maybe 100.
你知道我在想啥？我认为，我们应该庆祝一下
You know what I think? I think that we two should celebrate.
- 庆祝什么呢？ - 你自己的画廊新开幕啊
- Celebrate what? - That you have opened your own gallery.
- 敬我们 - 谢谢你对我的支持，罗杰
- And us. - Thank you for supporting me, Roger.
- 一切都会顺利的 - 你在说什么啊？
- Everything will be fine. - What do you mean?
事实上，我们应该开始思考未来
The fact that we two should start thinking about the future.
- 是的，是我 - 我们有一个新目标
- Yes, it's Ove. - We have a candidate.
- 你知道现在几点吗？ - 奥斯卡街25号 柯乐斯格雷夫宅
- Do you know what time it is? - Clas Greve, Oscars Street 25
- 这啥怪名字？ - 他是外国人
- Is there a count? - His name is Count.
奥雅纳？
Ove?
- 奥雅纳？怎么回事？ - 对不起 娜塔莎在这里
- Ove? What is happening? - Sorry. Natasha is here.
- 你刚说什么？ - 明天在老地方碰面
- What did you say? - Meet me at the house tomorrow.
不，明天不行！周末耶 我要陪她渡假
No, not tomorrow! It's Saturday. I have her all weekend.
最好是，奥雅纳 我们的时间不多
This is great, Ove. We only have a couple of days left.
- 一点钟！ - 好，很好
- At one O'clock! - Okay, Great.
- 你真体贴 - 早安
- How good you are. - Good morning.
- 你... ？ - 怎么 ？
- You ...? - Yes?
你昨天说，要思考的未来 ...
What you said yesterday to think about the future ...
有包括会在走廊上嬉闹的小小脚步声吗？
Includes the sound of small pattering feet in the corridors here?
- 也许吧 - 不要说也许，罗杰
- Maybe. - Do not say maybe, Roger.
我昨天说过一切都顺利的话
I said yesterday that everything will work out.
- 我希望你现在就说清楚 - 我也想，但我有一个重要会议要开
- I will have that conversation now. - Me too, but I'm going to an important meeting.
你开玩笑的吧？你有一个重要会议要开？
Do you think I'm stupid? You should be at an important meeting?
这是昨天夜里决定的？
It was decided last night?
我必须去 我们晚点在电话里谈
I must go. We can talk on the phone later.
- 你到底在怕什么？ - 没什么
- What are you so afraid of? - Nothing.
我怕狗 还有你，尤其是你现在这个样子
Dogs. And you, when you are like you are now.
如果你要我们下半辈子??都无子女，让我知道
If we are to be childless for the rest of my life, I know.
好，但现在我有一个重要会议要开
Yes, but now I am at an important meeting.
- 我试图跟你谈论它已经7年了 - 还要再 7年
- Have tried to talk about it for 7 years. - And it will take 7 years.
如果你继续这样唠叨的话！
If you continue to nag about it!
我不是有意的
It did not mean it.
你永远都不会给我一个孩子
You will never give me a child.
我们要谈的是几百万元？
How many millions are we talking about?
- 也许有一亿 - 一亿？
- Perhaps up to a hundred. - A hundred?!
你又来了，我说过，我不喜欢这东西
It's the same every time, Ove. I have said I do not want this stuff.
你知道我一直有武器
You know I always have weapons.
在家里我到处都有武器 每个房间都可以找到一把枪
At home I have weapons everywhere. Can reach a gun in every room.
你也应该带一把 有备无患
You should also get yourself one. Sooner or later they come.
好啦 你先去哥德堡取得复制品再说
Ok. You go to Gothenburg and obtain a reproduction.
我们必须好好干 我星期一会和柯乐斯吃午餐 ...
We must have a good thing. I will have lunch with Clas Greve on Monday ...
奥雅纳？
Ove?
- 我说过你待在车上！ - 可是，我要找打火机！
- I said you were going to be in the car! - But I have no fire!
出去！我们正在开会！
Out! We have a meeting here!
女人喔...
Women ...
在那个俄罗斯妓女打断我之前，我想说的是...
What I wanted to say before I was interrupted of a Russian whore ...
周一的午餐时，我会趁他不在 潜进他的公寓
At lunch Monday I will find out when the apartment is empty.
- 你现在就去瑞典 现在 - 好
- You go to Sweden again. Now. - Good.
- 不，不好 我有事要忙 - 有事要忙？
- No, fuck. I'm busy. - Busy?
娜塔莎在这里 我要跟她拍新‘电影’
Natasha is here. I'll record a new movie with her.
我跟同事都已经安排好了
I have arranged everything with the guys at work.
- 你偷拍她？ - 我总得有东西看吧
- You film her? - I must have something to watch.
我只要打开警报，摄影机就会拍了
I just turn on the alarm, then roll the cameras.
- 所以，她不知道你在拍摄？ - 不知道
- So she does not know that you are filming? - No.
你的同事就坐着看你们两个 ...？
And the guards are sitting and watching the two of you ...?
摄影机没有指着床啦！
I have no camera directed at the bed!
他们只会看到，她脱衣服，和一些指法 就是这样
They will see that she is undressing, and some fingering. That's it.
她开始了 真棒
She has cut itself. Fine.
其余细节不说了... 很美，对吗？
The rest is private. Fat, right?
再没几天，那幅画就要移走了
There are only a few days until the art is moved.
- 你知道时间多紧迫吗？ - 她一个学期才来两次
- Do you understand how big this is? - She is only here twice a semester.
你会赚好数百万
You will be left with millions.
有了这么多钱，你可以买下她了 你可以拍一辈子
With that much money you can buy her. For the rest of your life.
小龙虾果冻，酱料淋在旁边
I take it without crayfish jelly, and dressing on the side.
你现在就住奥斯陆了，还是要两地飞来飞去？
Are you in Oslo now, or will there be much commuting in the future?
350万元，加上股票期权
Three and a half million, plus stock options.
你有点漫天喊价  请记住，你是外国人
You take things a bit for granted. Remember that you are a foreigner.
挪威公司要的是...
Norwegian companies want ...
你掩饰的真好
Your method works safely at most.
但我们之前就碰过这种状况了
But we have been in this situation before.
- 你其实在嫉妒我... - 嫉妒你？
- You literally drooling ... - Drooling?
当我们在画廊碰面时 就感到你的嫉妒 不是吗？
You were drooling when we met in the gallery. You did right in.
只有一个问题，我对工作不感兴趣
The problem was only I was not interested in the job.
但是我发现，翻修老公寓真的是很繁琐
But I found that renovating the apartment is not as exciting.
因此，如果你不介意  ...我们别再装了
So if it's OK for you ... Let's just drop the play.
好的 我放弃
Ok. I give up.
- 但我需要更多的信息 - 你玩壁球吗？
- But I need more information. - Do you play squash?
- 结婚了 ？ - 离婚了
- Married? - Divorced.
- 有小孩？ - 抱歉没
- Children? - Sorry.
- 有养狗？ - 是，我有
- Dog? - Yes. I have.
- 它还在阿姆斯特丹 - 要检疫？
- In Amsterdam. - Quarantine?
我会飞回去，明天接它来
I fly down and pick it up tomorrow.
GPS业有这么惨烈喔？
It's hard in the GPS industry?
- 你的背 - 不是 ...是军队给我的
- Your back. - Nah ... It is from the army.
我 18岁就从军了
I enlisted as an 18-year-old.
几年后，我加入了一个特殊的单位 ...
After a few years I ended in a special unit ...
- 怎样特殊法？ - 追踪
- Specializing in what? - Tracking.
- 追踪... ？ - 追踪人
- Tracking ...? - People.
失踪人口 通缉要犯
Missing. Wanted.
- 用‘贺得’提供的技术？ - 正确
- And the technology was provided by HOTE? - Exactly.
他们在开发微型发报器
They made microscopic transmitters.
我提了些改进的建议 于是他们请我加入
I had suggestions for improvements. So they recruited me.
- 那疤痕是哪来的？ - 玻利维亚
- Where are the scars from? - Bolivia.
- 你被敌人折磨？ - 还好被即时救出来
- Were you tortured? - No, I was released on time.
- 听起来像一部电影 - 不，这是真实情节
- Sounds like something from a movie. - No, you have not seen the movie.
- 我们什么时候能跟‘探路者’开会？ - 任何时候！
- When can we have a meeting with Pathfinder? - Anytime.
- 你什么时候回来？ - 后天
- When are you back? - The day after tomorrow.
那好，就后天
So we take it then.
戴安娜？
Diana?
嗨，我是戴安娜，我现在不能接听电话 祝你有愉快的一天
Hey, it's Diana. I can not answer the phone now. Have a nice day.
- 哈罗 - 终于回来啦
- Hello. - So there you are.
- 我有打你的手机 没通 - 我一定是忘在画廊了
- I tried to call you on your mobile. - I must have forgotten it at the gallery.
- 有重要的事吗？ - 没
- Was it something important? - No.
只是想听听你的声音
I just wanted to hear your voice.
你很可爱 快来坐下，电影才刚刚开始
You are cute. Come and sit down, a movie has just started.
不，我...
No. I ...
我累坏了 我要去睡觉
I am totally exhausted. I'll go to bed.
好吧
Ok.
我们开发了一种发胶，一小撮里就有上百个发报器
We developed a gel that contains hundreds of transmitters per ml.
能附着任何物体，绝对不会脱落
It sticks to everything, and is impossible to remove.
这样就能追踪
You mean Trace.
缺点是，沾上污泥会干扰它
The weakness is that Trace is sensitive to mud, for example.
这是我从军时的经验
This I know from experience as a soldier.
当你处在他妈的，对不起，险恶的环境里...
When you are in, excuse me, the world's butt hole ...
可信赖的设备会救你一命
When you are dependent on equipment that works.
还好您请罗杰布朗来帮忙，否则我们可能不会碰面
That you are using Brown, is clearly of great importance.
归根结底，还由他来介绍我这个人比较好
Ultimately, it is he that must make his recommendation.
抱歉，我失陪一下
For a moment, only.
- 非常好 - 谢谢您！
- Very good. - Thank you.
你何时会写我的介绍信？
When are you writing your recommendation?
- 我们必须考虑一下 - 你说什么？
- We must make a decision first. - What do you say?
有好几个候选人 我们必须看到大局 你会收到通知的
There are several candidates. We must see the overall picture. You will be notified.
你不是和我们一起开会？它不能更好了
Have we been at the same meeting? It could not have gone better.
- 他们几乎都要在合约上签字了 - 真这样就好
- They were ready to sign the contract. - Then you are well too.
嗨！你今晚就去哥德堡，奥雅纳
Hello. You travel to Gothenburg tonight, Ove.
那张画必须尽早脱手
The picture will be sold as soon as possible.
嗨！我要和你谈谈
Hello. I need to talk to you.
- 你不能找我 - 你就不能给我几分钟？
- You can not find me. - Can't you give me two seconds?
对不起，你会这样，都是我的错，但我们已经...
I am sorry if it's my fault that you have it so, but we have ...
我们之间真的没啥好谈的
There really is nothing more to talk about.
- 你需要钱吗？ - 我好想念你
- Do you need money? - I miss you so much.
罗悌 ...
Lotte ...
罗悌 ...不要再与我联络了
Lotte ... Do not contact me again.
- 你看来累坏了 - 谢谢
- You look tired. - Thank you.
- 有什么事吗？ - 没
- Is there something? - No.
- 你工作是不是很辛苦？ - 是的，一点点
- Is there a lot going at work? - Yes, a little.
我今天与探路者开会  还有柯乐斯格雷夫
I had a meeting with Pathfinder today. And Clas Greve.
- 你没事吧？ - 没
- Are you Okay? - No.
- 他没有录取吗？ - 绝对不会录取
- He does not get the job? - Absolutely not.
明天我会打电话给其他仲介
Tomorrow I'll call the other agencies.
我要确保他在挪威找不到任何工作
I will ensure that he does not get a job in Norway.
为什么？
Why?
你找到你的手机了吗？
Did you find your mobile, by the way?
- 你的手机不是丢了 - 找到了
- You had lost your mobile. - Yes.
- 在画廊？ - 没错
- At the Gallery? - Yes.
- 好 再喝一杯？ - 好，谢谢你
- Well. More wine? - Yes, thank you.
奥雅纳？
Ove?
奥雅纳 ...
Ove ...
- 嗨 - 你怎么跑来了？
- Hey. - What are you doing here?
你进来好久，却没有出来
You went down here, and did not come out.
- 我很担心 - 担心什么？
- I was worried. - About what?
没事
Nothing.
- 罗杰 你... - 怎么？
- You Roger ... - Yes?
祝你今天工作顺利，还有
Have a nice day at work, then.
我爱你
I love you.
奥雅纳！
Ove!
- 奥雅纳，你住在哪里？ - 娜塔莎...
-Ove, where do you live? -Natasha ...
奥雅纳 ...奥雅纳！
Ove ... Ove!
你住在哪里... ？
Where do you live...?
奥雅纳，你在车库发生了什么事？
Ove, what happened in the garage?
你看到有人吗？
Did you see anyone?
快回答我
Answer me now.
你有看到发生了什么事吗？有别人吗？
Did you see what happened? Was there anyone there?
- 娜塔莎... - 什么？
- Natasha ... - What?
这到底是怎么回事？
What the hell is going on here?
奥雅纳，密码是什么？
Ove, what is the password?
- 保全的密码 - 娜塔莎...
- The password for the alarm. - Natasha ...
我们要关掉保全警报 密码是什么？
We need to disable the alarm. What is the password?
- 密码是什么！ - 我说的就是密码！是娜塔莎！
- What is my password! - This is what I am saying! Natasha!
是沙 还是 撒？
Sh or Ch?
奥雅纳 ...
Ove ...
奥雅纳，怎么回事？
Ove, how's it going?
- 怎么啦？ - 你坐到我车上的注射器
- What happened? - You sat on a syringe in the car.
注射器？
A syringe?
- 你很幸运了 - 幸运？！
- You have been lucky. - Lucky?!
针头只碰到了你的膝盖 毒药没有完全渗透
You got the needle in the knee. The poison does not penetrate properly.
- 是你任务搞砸了？ - 这是因为别的事！
- Have you fucked up? - This is about something else!
戴安娜与 柯乐斯格雷夫有染
Diana has a relationship with Clas Greve.
他要杀了你，因为他想上你的老婆！
He doesn't kill you because he is fucking your wife!
- 那，快报警！ - 不能让警察发现这里！
- Call 112, then! - We shall have no police up here!
拜托，罗杰 我需要去医院
Please, Roger. I need to go to the hospital.
- 否则，我死定了 - 我去拿牛奶
- Otherwise, I die. - I'll get the milk.
牛奶会中和毒物 他们在医院也只会做这个
Milk neutralizes poison. They would have done nothing else in the hospital.
- 打电话！ - 别做傻事
- Call. - Do not do anything stupid.
那我自己打
Then I do it myself.
现在，我们都冷静下来 ...
Now we take it very quietly ...
罗杰 我要和你谈谈
Roger. I have to talk to you.
我花了我大半辈子在追踪人
I have spent most of my adult life tracking down people.
..微型发报机
Microscopic transmitters.
你好 我想要去小屋
Good day. Have thought of taking a short trip to the cottage.
- 我还以为是奥雅纳 - 不是
- I thought it was Kjikerud. - No.
- 这是他的车 - 没错
- It is his car. - Yes.
- 你不是那些商人之一吗？ - 我被炒鱿鱼了
- Aren't you one of those businessmen? - I got fired.
- 我可以把车停在谷仓吗？ - 每天500元
- Can I put the car in the barn? - 500 per day.
你随便停在路旁就不用钱了
You can get free down the road, you know.
如果你要用拖拉机的话，要另外收费！
If you drive the tractor, then I want compensation!
- 私人土地 进去要钱喔！ - 我只是要找罗杰布朗
- the amount of legwork here today! - I'm just going to visit Roger Brown.
- 要找那个商人？ - 没错
- Is he a businessman? - Yes.
- 要找他做什么呢？ - 我们要谈个交易
- What are you doing with him? - We have a deal.
你们要做什么，我都没有意见，但是...
I have nothing to do with what you are doing, but ...
他们租的小木屋 使用人不包括你喔
He has not invited you for coffee and cakes at the cabin.
租的小木屋？
At the cabin?
由于它是我的财产，你要使用也要付钱
Since it is my property, some compensation is perhaps reasonable.
去搜索！
Search!
哈罗？
Hello?
你是谁？
Who are you?
哦，哦天啊 ...
Oh, oh hell ...
你不该起来！
You should not stay up!
- 有没有人问起我？ - 没有，过来躺下
- Has anyone asked for me? - No. Come and lie down again.
除了警察 他们坐在在走廊上等你醒来
Apart from the police. They are sitting waiting for you in the hallway.
我说等你吃过早餐再说
I said you should eat breakfast first.
因为你可能面临情况 ...你擅长搏斗吗？
Because if you manage to turn into ....., are you good at fighting.
有听说过升龙拳吗？
Ever heard of co-daw-ying?
没有吧 你知道世上有多少种武术吗？ 三千种
Not so strange.Do you know how many martial arts there? 3000.
埃及的武术 ...
Egyptian martial arts ...
站住
Stand still!
松代，我逮到他了！
Sunded, I got him!
我是奥拉夫 松代, 犯罪调查局的
Olav Sunded from NCIS.
你涉嫌谋杀农民 辛得勒
You are suspected of murdering of the farmer Sindre Aa.
奥雅纳先生，跟我们进去休息
Join us Kjikerud, we will rest inside.
你是奥雅纳没错吧？
You are Ove Kjikerud?
没错
Yes.
- 我们要去哪里？ - 要带你回警署问话
- Where are we? - Elverum Police Station for questioning.
希望您能合作，这样我明天才可以去奥斯陆
Hope you cooperate, so I can go to Oslo tomorrow.
- 所有的巡逻车请注意 - 他们两个也希望你合作
- Notice to all patrol cars. - Both of them, in other words.
B30 回报. 请说状况
Bravo 3-0 answers.
卡尔森来报案 他的卡车失窃
Egmon Karlsen has reported his truck stolen.
- 卡尔森的声音听起来是清醒的吗？ - 不像，没很清醒
- Did Karlsen sound like he was sober? - Not entirely, no.
打给巴姆斯酒吧 他可能停在那忘了
Call Bamse pub. It is probably parked there.
- 你为什么要杀那个农民呢？ - 我不知道你在说什么
- Why did you murder the farmer, then? - I have no idea what you're talking about.
你把宾士车停在他的谷仓
Your Mercedes was in Sindre Aa's barn.
- 然后把他的拖拉机开进山沟里 - 我从来没有听说过他的名字
- You drove his tractor into the ditch. - I have never heard the name.
- 巴姆斯酒吧外没有车 - 我现在有更重要的案子要办
-  No truck outside the Bamse pub. - I have more important things to do now.
那去旗威酒吧外找！
Check behind the Kiwi.
抱歉
Sorry.
- 我们有几个证据 ... - 卡车在那，该死！
- We have several witnesses ... - There it is, of course, damn!
打给卡尔森 我看到了卡车 我猜是他儿子偷开出来的
Call Egmon. I see the truck. Surely the son was the thief who borrowed it.
你想做什么，兄弟？
What do you do now, Brugd?
正如我刚说的 我们有很多的证据
As I said. We have much evidence.
你无可抵赖的
And you flatly deny.
请你告诉我那些，我们不清楚的细节
Then you tell me details, for I know nothing.
农夫的邻居发现你倒在路边，拖拉机在山沟里
Aa's neighbor found you in the ditch next to the tractor.
我们开发了一种发胶，一小撮里就有上百个发报器
We developed a gel that contained hundreds of transmitters per ml.
能附着任何物体，绝对不会脱落
It sticks to everything, and is impossible to remove.
我爱你
I love you.
- 我们快离开 - 不行
- We have to leave. - No.
他会杀了我们 他在我的头发上装了发报器！
He's going to kill us. He has smeared my hair with transmitters!
- 冷静！ - 他在我的头发上装了发报器！
- Calm down! - He has smeared my hair with transmitters!
- 他会杀了我！ - 冷静下来！
- He will kill me! - Calm down!
我们一定要离开！
We must get out!
你好，我是戴安娜
Hey, it's Diana.
哈罗？
Hello?
喂？罗杰，是你吗？
Hello? Roger, is that you?
在这之后，我们去法医那
After this we go to Forensic.
然后我们去看奥雅纳的房子
Then we take a look at Kjikerud's house
“我是乡下来的女孩 ，你是挪威最性感的警察 ”
"I am a single girl from Gjovik. You are Norway's sexiest policeman. "
“也是最聪明的，能碰个面吗？我随时有空 ”
"And the smartest. Will you meet me? I'm with the majority. "
这里到底发生了什么事？
What the hell happened here?
罗悌，等等 是我
Lotte, wait.
- 你来这里做什么？发生了什么事？ - 我需要帮忙
- What are you doing here? What has happened? - I need help. Please.
- 我不想连累到你 - 连累什么？
- I do not want to drag you into this. - Into what?
他们问起时，不必说谎 就说，我来过
When they ask, do not lie. Just say that I was here.
就说你是被我逼的
Just say that I forced myself in.
发生了什么事？
What has happened?
等着 我去拿东西来做清洁
Wait here. I'll get something to clean it with.
你有没有剪刀？
Do you have a pair of scissors?
罗悌，你在跟谁联络？
Lotte, who are you contacting?
- 电话给我！ - 住手
- Give me the phone! - Stop.
- “罗杰还活着，他在公寓 ” - 不是你想的那样...
- "Roger is alive. He is in the apartment." - It's not what you think ...
- 这是怎么回事？ - 我也不知道！
- What is going on? - I do not know!
- 这不是我的错！ - 这是怎么回事？
- It's not my fault! - What is going on?
- 拜托你... - 格雷夫到底为什么找我？
- Please ... - What does Greve want with me?
- 他想在‘探路者’工作 - 没有人会为求职杀人吧！
- He wants the job in Pathfinder. - You do not kill for a job!
这关系到几十亿元
It's about billions.
他们自从发现了探路者在找一个新经理人时，就努力在争取
They have been working with it since they found out Pathfinder is looking for a new manager.
- “他们”是谁？！ - 柯乐斯
- Who are 'they'?! - Clas.
- 他仍然在为‘贺得’工作 - 什么？
- He still works for HOTE. - What?
- 什么？ - 他们有庞大的财政问题
- What?! - They have huge financial problems.
美国人要求他们必须取得探路者的技术 才会金援
Amtech requires HOTE to provide them with Pathfinder technology.
- 这就是柯乐斯的任务 - 你疯了吗？
- It was Clas' task. - Are you insane?
我的任务是认识你，然后向你介绍他
I was going to teach you to recognize, and then introduce you to him.
但是因为你不想见我了，他不得不改变计划
He had to make a new plan, because you did not want to see me anymore.
他必须另外设法来认识你
He had to find a way to meet you.
他的祖母有一张复制的鲁本斯油画
His grandmother had an old copy of a Rubens painting.
他捏造了她跟德国军官的故事
He concocted a story about her getting it from a German officer.
他把故事告诉戴安娜，她相信了
He told Diana the story and she believed him.
然后，他遇见了你
Then he met you.
我做的只是在你的头发上抹了发报器
The only thing I did was to smear the transmitters in your hair.
原来你知道？
Did you know?
原来是你在我的头发上抹那玩意！
Is it you who smeared the shit in my hair!
- 戴安娜也有份吗？ - 我不知道 我想是有
- Is Diana involved? - I do not know. I think so.
- 你想她有？ - 我也不愿意发生这种事！
- You think so?! - It's not me who wants this!
我只是想远离他 你能不能帮我？
I just want away from him. Can't you help me?
可以给我一杯水吗？
Can I get a glass of water?
罗悌！
Lotte!
犯罪嫌疑人，随着三名警察在事故中丧生
The suspect died in the accident along with three of the four police officers.
幸存的一名警务人员仍然下落不明
The last police officer is still missing.
陆军的潜水员正在沿河寻找 另外，中东的局势方面 ...
Army divers are now searching along the river. Now, to Middle East ...
戴安娜
Diana.
罗杰？
Roger?
发生了什么事？
What has happened?
不要这样看我
Do not look at me that way.
我知道你为什么离开  柯乐斯和我之间没有什么的
I know why you left. There is nothing more between Clas and me.
那天在车库里我试着要讲清楚，可是没办法
I tried to put it in the garage, but could not.
- 但你怎么知道 ... ？ - 不，先让我说完
- But what do you know ...? - No, I have to say this now.
这一切都只是意外 但是，你伤害了我
It was not meant to happen. But you hurt me.
他是很容易谈得来的人，可是我...
He was so easy to talk to, and I just ...
根本无法了解他
Couldn't keep up anymore.
这是错误的 我很惭愧
It was wrong. And I am ashamed of myself.
你才是我想要的人
For it is you I want.
如果你真的相信，我们不需要孩子，那么我们就不要生
If you really believe that we do not have children, then we don't need to.
我愿意为你做任何事情
I am willing to to do anything.
你是爱我的，你...
You love me, you ...
相信我 我永远只爱你一个人
Never stop believing in it. Promise me that.
- 你原来都不知情 - 不知道什么？
- And you knew nothing. - About what?
原来你都不知情
You knew nothing.
哦，我的天 发生了什么事？
Oh, my God. What has happened?
跟我来
Come.
被狗咬伤很危险的 你必须让医生看看
Dog bites are dangerous. You must let a doctor look at it.
现在就医不太适合
It is a little bad right now.
扶着
Hold this.
- 你准备要怎么办？ - 我不知道
- What are you going to do now? - I don't know.
他们很快就会发现，在事故中死亡的不是我
They will soon find out who died in the accident.
我必须要毁灭证据
I have to remove the evidence.
然后呢？
And then?
我必须离开这里 从头开始
I must get away from here. Start over again.
也许我俩可以...
Maybe the two of us could ...
先拿去用，我晚一点再报失窃
I can wait a little and report it stolen.
你还要清理一下
I have to clean them too.
你爱她吗？
Do you love her?
不爱
No.
你怎么会这么愚蠢？
How could you be so fucking stupid?
偷艺术品？买我不需要的东西给我？
Steal art? And buy things I don't need?
你把我当作什么啦？
Who do you think I am?
你曾问过我，我害怕什么
You have asked me what I fear.
从认识你以来，我一直担心害怕
And I have been afraid since the first time I met you.
我一直害怕有天你会离开我
I have been afraid that you would leave me.
害怕我们有了孩子后，你比较爱他而不爱我
Afraid that we would have a child that you would have loved more than me.
更令我害怕的是，你会看清楚我的本性
And I have been afraid that you would see who I really was.
进而憎恨我
And hate it.
- 对此深表遗憾，格雷夫 - 没有关系
- Sorry about this, Greve. - It's all right.
罗杰布朗临时出差到国外去了
Roger Brown is on an unexpected trip abroad.
- 听起来怪怪的 - 他去抢救一份重要的合约
- It sounds interesting. - He had to rescue an important contract.
但现在你还是可以放心 因为程序依然在走
But you are in safe hands now. Only formalities remain.
因此，还是会很顺利进行的
So it will probably move quickly.
您好！我们要去修理 B4的风扇
Hello. We would switch a fan on B4.
我们必须整天进进出出 但这张卡好像失效了
We have gone back and forth across all day. But this card doesn't work.
（法医研究室/ 病理部)
谢谢
Thank you.
嘿，伙计们 很抱歉，进度有点落后
Hey, guys. Sorry, but we are a little behind here.
刚处理掉一个女人，她被热死已经14天了
Just got a woman who has been lying dead in the heat for 14 days.
- 那么，你觉得这是什么情况？ - 两个人都是典型的车祸受伤
- What do you think about this, then? - Typical injuries from a car accident to both.
- 死亡的原因 是内部出血 - 那包花生在哪里？
- Internal bleeding is the cause of death. - Where are the peanuts?
文件上说，这里有一包花生 它在哪里？
It says that there would be a bag of peanuts. Where is it?
我可没吃掉喔
I have not eaten them.
- 有人未经许可来过这里？ - 来偷一包花生吗？
- Has someone unauthorized been here? - To steal a bag of peanuts?
那是谁？
Who is it?
这到底是怎么回事，罗杰？
What the hell is going on here, Roger?
想湮灭证据吗？你认为你可以这样脱身吗？
Removing evidence? Do you think you can get away with this?
搞什么？
What the hell?
原来你把头发都剃了？发报机在上头说
So you did it with the hair? That's where the transmitters were.
这是罗悌干的...
That it was Lotte, who ...
- 你为了这个杀了她？ - 你会伤心吗？
- That's why you killed her? - Does it feel like a loss?
我给你一个选择
I give you a choice.
告诉你是怎么回事，你是想要头部中弹
Tells you what is going on, and you will get a shot in the head.
- 还是，你比较想要腹部中弹 - 你有没有人性？
- Otherwise, you get a bullet in the stomach. - Have you no feelings about it?
我想知道你这样的人 活着有什么意思？
I want to know what people like you really are.
我这样的人？
Like me?
没法爱人的人 没办法将心比心的人
People who can not love. Who are without empathy.
- 将心比心？ - 没错
- Empathy? - Yes.
如果你想知道答案，自己照照镜子
If you want an answer to it, look in the mirror.
- 我才不像你 - 你不像吗？
- I am not like you. - Aren't you?
不像
No.
- 我有深爱的人 - 你有深爱的人？ 戴安娜？
- I have loved someone. - You have loved someone? Diana?
你爱她吗？
Her you loved?
恐怕我有噩耗要告诉你
I'm afraid I have sad news.
她说，她渴望我 她需要我
She says she longs for me. She wants me.
我也只是凡人
And I'm only human.
你真的爱她吗？比爱你那条死狗还爱？
Have you loved someone? Someone other than your dead dog?
我没空说闲话了 我跟戴安娜今晚还有约
I don't have time for this. I have an appointment with Diana tonight.
你剃了你的头发 你知道我会来找你 为什么呢？
You got your hair. You know I will come after you. Why?
腹部中弹而死需要很长的时间，你会求我给你一个痛快
It takes a long time to die of a stomach shot. You will beg me to kill you.
所以我问你最后一次：我为什么来这里？
So I ask you one last time: Why am I here?
你在笑什么？我为什么来这里？
Why are you smiling? Why am I here?
不准动！
Stop that!
你知道为什么我笑了吗，柯乐斯？
Do you know why I smiled, Clas?
因为你刚刚证明了，戴安娜爱的是我
Because you just proved that Diana loves me.
她去找你，并非因为她想你
She did not come to you because she wanted you.
她是去掉包你的手枪子弹
She came to replace bullets in your gun.
她是拿空包弹 去掉包你的手枪子弹
She has replaced the bullets in your gun. With loose shots.
你们丹麦语怎么说？空白子弹？
Or what do you call them in Denmark? Blanks?
- 你他妈的在说什么？ - 她恨你
- What the hell are you talking about? - She hates you.
她希望你死
She wants you to die.
但是，我给你一个机会
But I'll give you one chance.
我不知道戴安娜掉包了多少子弹
I have no idea how many bullets Diana managed to replace.
这不像你，柯乐斯 ...
It is not like you, Clas ...
结束了吗？
Is it over?
是的
Yes.
我可能不够了解自己，但对人性 我了若指掌
I may not know myself, but others. I will gamble on that.
这场新闻发表会 是由奥斯陆警方和调查局所招开
Welcome to this press conference under the auspices of the Oslo police and NCIS.
我自己已经准备妥当
I had prepared myself well.
我在车祸现场拿的警用手枪，警方在奥雅纳床头柜上找到
Service pistol from the crash which the Police find in Kjikerud's bedside table.
同一把枪打死了罗悌马德森，媒体说她是格雷夫的情妇
The same gun killed Lotte Madsen, which the press called Greve's mistress.
至于“艺品大盗”奥雅纳 和柯乐斯格雷夫是如何杀死对方 ...
How "art thieves" Ove Kjikerud and Clas Greve killed each other ...
全世界的人在网路上都看得到
The whole world has seen on the internet.
而他们也发现格雷夫发射的枪
They would also learn the gun Greve fired, -
弹道和贯穿奥雅纳头的子弹是一致的
- Is consistent with the bullet that perforated Ove's head.
他当初不应该拿那把枪的
He should have never taken the gun.
案情的进展 可谓大有突破
We can present a breakthrough in the case.
我做的一切都天衣无缝 但有一件事我没法改变
I had done everything right. But one thing I could not change.
我射杀格雷夫时，奥雅纳早就死了
Ove was already dead when I shot Greve.
但是布雷德是全挪威最著名的神探
But Brede Sperre is Norway's most famous detective.
无法侦破的悬案不是他的风格 特别是在媒体都这样称呼他的时候：
Unresolved issues are not his style. Especially not after VG called him:
“这名男子让挪威人夜里安心入睡 ”
"The man who makes Norway sleep soundly at night. "
就因为他是神探？当然是罗
Because he's good? Absolutely.
但是他要是真想搞清楚 整件事的来龙去脉怎么办呢？
But mostly because he understood what leads to upward and forward. And what is it?
这真是一个漫长而复杂的调查
It has been a long and complicated investigation.
关键在于‘作者的名字’
The answer begins with "r".
人的声誉啊
Reputation.
让一个人上电视，花痴女主播问他两句话他就飘到天上去了
Get one on TV, and receive text messages from strange women.
我们认为，嫌犯本来是要庆祝窃案得手，结果场面完全失控
We think they celebrated the theft, and it went completely out of control.
他们进而虐杀了狗，杀了无辜农民
Eventually they torture a dog, and kill the farmer.
完全正确
That is correct.
有个愉快的一天 你们俩个
Have a nice day. Both of you.
- 我们已经准备好 - 告诉候选人 再一分钟出来
- We are ready. - Tell the candidate about a minute.
费迪南德 ...谢谢你
Ferdinand ... Thank you.
您好！我们深表歉意 请就座
Hello. We're sorry. Please be seated.
我邀请你们到这里来，是因为我们已到了最后阶段
I have asked you to come here because we are in the final phase of-
探路者的新经理职位经过漫长和戏剧性的寻觅
- A long and dramatic hunting for Pathfinder's new boss.
最近对方才不太情愿的离开他的现职
Most recently it was unrealistic to have him relieved of his position.
我没承诺他很多，我想我已经争取到他加入了
Without promising too much, I think I've got him on the plain.
让我为您介绍 ... 耶利米兰德 先生
Please welcome ... Jeremiah Lander.
上次很感谢你
Thank you for last time.
我叫罗杰布朗，身高只有168公分
My name is Roger Brown. I am 1.68.
而你知道吗？这已经是绰绰有余了
And you know what? That is more than enough.
字幕： Circle did it for Joan
校对： 小霸王比比?  ＆娃娃